John it's really great to have you back
thanks for joining us it's a pleasure to
be here again we've been really excited
to follow your work and deeply
appreciative of seeing you make use of
some of my work so I wanted to thank you
for that in person I'm so really it
really happy to be here
yeah so for those of you watching this
is gonna be more of a conversation less
of a strict interview where I'm gonna be
sharing some ideas with John and giving
his feedback on them so what we've been
working on is a kind of a map of of what
evolved play is all about and right yeah
you know we've talked about this idea of
the ecology of practices before very
much we've been trying to break down
like what what is it that we're doing
what are all these pieces and you know
we've come up with essentially there's a
set of body practices like there's a
practices within the body and how the
body relates to things okay right
practice that's kind of like a
meditation that's internal that's about
the body right you know body integrity
practice like how do I make sure this
thing that I'm in or this thing that is
me is sustained and functions and as
good a relationship between all those
component pizzas as possible right and
then how do I then then there's the body
to environment practice how do i how do
I make more sophisticated more
differentiated more confident my
relationship to the environment around
me the stacking from Moroni there's a
body to object practice right where to
you know the environment is the things
that we move ourselves on and the
objects of the things that we can move
right that's the way people then move
things that becomes a really interesting
place where there's lots of stuff to
practice and then there's ourselves in
other bodies body to bodies right that's
the center of our or our physical
practices and what we do is really at
that point right like we're that the
body people like um you know I've been
enjoying listening to your turning to
your podcast series or your
your lecture series I've been enjoying
interested in your talks with guys hang
stock and Jordan Hall and all these guys
but the one thing that I'm always asking
is where is the body in this store sure
well I do I do I do constantly say that
body practices have to be in the ecology
practices and and and I often point to
your work in fact as exemplifying a
community of practice that it's creating
an ecology practices so yeah very much I
agree with that and and I you know and
at some point with my talk about some of
the some of the phenomena that earmark
that like when you for example a body
environment relationship if you're
coupled very well for the environment
you probably going to get into the flow
state and what does that look like and
things like that so but yes I very much
agree with what you've said and then
there's another way in which my work
converges with it because as you know I
advocate for for ecard of science and
for understanding cognition as you know
embodied embedded you know extended etc
and so well I don't often talk about it
as concretely as you do I think what
you're doing is very convergent though
the work I'm doing with guy and Jordan
is and you know it we do talk about the
embodied aspects for the reasons I've
just articulated but right now we're
really focused on trying to get trying
to get a cyclo technology for dialogue
that's analogous to what the ancient
practice of dialectic was so that we
learn how to activate collective
intelligence with industry within
distributed cognition and in a way
that's analogous to individual cognition
the way individual intelligence can be
bootstrapped in to rationality and into
wisdom I'm trying to figure out can we
create can we create a psycho technology
dialectic that activates dialogue within
collective intelligence so it can be
bootstrapped into collective rationality
and collective wisdom so that's why
that's thanks well that's why that's for
granted right now because I think is
that that is to use Jordan strim that's
a meta psycho technology that all the
groups like your group will need that
too because part of what like I see you
doing right
you're also getting into dialogue and
we're doing it right now and so how can
we optimize that dialogue so the
dissemination and the cultivation for
you of the embodied ecology practices
could be can happen much more fluently
much more effectively in a much more
flowing manner yeah yeah so so actually
I am so movement is at the center what
we do and we want to like be really
clear about that but what we've
recognized is that our orientation
around movement is how it transforms
people right X others do we notice that
movement does this thing to people then
we can look at these these other streams
these other ecologies these other
practices and how they can assist in
them we want to excellentest on where
where our expertise is you know and and
kind of like no no what are centrist
it's not everyone's Center it's not the
center that myth necessary is essential
for that's our Center but with the
movement then there's a mindfulness
piece yes a community piece and this is
what yes I believe that you were you
were challenging me on this the last
time I'm calling your somewhere yes yeah
yeah so I've written that in now and
then there's the nature piece right a
relationship yeah so you know I've taken
the distinction that I learned from you
of meditation contemplation and I've
actually been using so what we've been
doing is a combination of focused
practice that I learned from rice from
Simon Fackler or toggler sorry you know
I do either was obviously just the
breath but I like to focus on a single
point and try to collapse yeah that
point right to to learn to control
attention
I find that practice is somewhat
disembodied though yes
yeah I like to couple that with a body
scan meditation and then I will
transition from that once I have I feel
like I've attuned and improved my
ability to to control attention then I
do a meta meditation excellence I
actually taught to me by our mutual
friend Mark Walsh ah excellent and
that's but that's actually really
profound effects it's quite interesting
okay that's that's the core approach
though
let me go to go deep in and then deep
out and then learning how to flow
between them that's why the movement
practices also tie in right because the
movement practices give your brain that
interactive schema of how to move in and
out so I see like when I'm doing Tai Chi
Chuan you're literally doing the
in-and-out movement but that is
overlapping with the eating out of
attention that you're doing in the
private practices so the movement
mindfulness and the sit-in mindfulness
can talk deeply to each other
yeah and I think it's really interesting
because the you know I always like to at
least return to like my base frame right
it's like if I'm gonna teach martial
arts I need to at least know that the
things that I'm teaching or helping
people fight right yes yeah yeah like
everything else that I claim has to sort
of not ignore this most basic principle
right
so when I think about meditation I also
recognize that it actually it the
meditation trains my ability to focus on
the thing that I need to focus in the
moment when I'm actually moving and that
without that I'm a bird
that that's one of the biggest dangers
that we face is our attention being on
the wrong thing
like most of our movements it's because
your attention has shifted too early
right right so you're you're looking
ahead in the sequence or it's just
shifted completely out of the frame
right after you're moving and suddenly
you have a thought about your girlfriend
fall down all right but and so that
ability to attune and train the
attention is actually incredibly
critical to successfully completing the
movements and of course that all it
connects in in flow state and then I
guess it goes the other way too right as
I learned in the park or informed by the
mindfulness to more appropriately
distribute my attention that should then
ramify out into my life in general right
yeah that's the idea
so so like why do parkour in addition to
meditation might be the opposite
question right yeah yeah one question is
why do why would a parkour athlete want
to do meditation but the second question
would be like why would a meditator want
to do
our core and those are both good
questions yeah and and the reason that I
might recommend that parque loro
meditator is kind of what you just
mentioned which is this idea that
essentially we're making physical the
processes that people are trying to
apply in their mind yeah this is where
like I really love the embodied and
embodied and embedded right yeah very
much where it's like you can train the
mind but if it isn't in relationship to
the body it's missing this tremendous
aspect because you know this is one of
things I love about your work you make
so clear that how we think is
extraordinarily conditioned on the fact
that we have bodies right over our
bodies we are bodies yeah how much of
our how much of our thinking is is
framed in analogies of the body to
understand to have it on something yes
very much
and so I think it's very easy on a
culture to lose sight of this but when
we make a more erudite body oh I like
that that's a nice turn of phrase yeah I
I just I was actually um I was reading
uh I was trying to find this quote that
I thought I had heard from like
epictetus about wrestling being the
foundation of physical culture and I
couldn't find it maybe it's a
misattribution but I started reading
about how Plato was a wrestler I'm guys
from wrestling what does that very much
and so yeah gymnastic and athletic
metaphors are pervasive through Plato
wrestling with philosophy yeah yeah
which i think is quite interesting and
it's interesting because you don't have
a association now one does not expect a
philosopher to be a physical
practitioner no and that's unfortunate I
mean I think that's more the case if
you'll all have a desire to kids in
Western philosophy and what you might
find in in AZ attic philosophy yeah so
and then the contemplation is also
really interesting because
I think that when you start having that
orientation towards towards wanting to
bring good into the world right it helps
regulate in motion and regulation of
emotion is actually super key to
athletic performance as well that's
something I think is it's massively
under understood is how much people's
frustration fear sadness anger etc is
actually the thing that has to be
addressed and work from them to make
progress yeah I think that's very well
said it's very well said III think that
I mean come from what I know within like
Tai Chi Chuan
and but also what I've read about in
gymnastics in ancient Greece I mean one
of the functions of the athletic
endeavors was to afford people exactly
that kind of training learning you know
very very much in the power of an
exigent moment to exercise self
regulation of emotion I think is one of
the key things yeah and I think that so
yes we have that that interaction again
where where the the mindfulness gives us
something as an athletic tool but then
the athletic practice gives us a window
into and a place to build
characteristics this is exactly what is
one of the features because I'm trying
to do this meta thing right now when I'm
trying to get at you know what are we
looking for an ecology of practice and
one of them one of the things I've
talked about is the checks and balances
but also this other thing you're talking
the way they they mutually
interpenetrate a mutually afford each
other right that's also a really
important thing that you want to be
looking for I would argue in an oncology
practices you because if they don't do
this if they don't sort of impregnate
each other with transformation then
you're not going to have a very you're
not gonna have a very dynamic
self-organizing system yeah so what
comes up in my head then is this is this
general question that I have about the
emergence of dynamical systems as a as a
as a reframing from an excessive
reductionism so I want to get into that
with you I think maybe a really deep
line of inquiry but I want to just go
through this this this little boys
please they might a might give you the
kind of feedback that you'd like that go
and I'm not just thinking too much I'm
just trying to comment along please do
please do I am I'm this is a little new
because I'm used to when I interview
people having my interviewer persona and
balance that between like how would I
talk to John if it was just me and John
talking well see if this is also helping
me because this is exemplifying this
process of dialogue and trying to get an
emergence like of the logos in the
dialogue so that it starts to take a
shape of its own and leads us into
places that are insightful and
transformative for us sweet so what I'm
an extra dear is I just I was I'm Anna
staphon I - I didn't know if I had done
this but I I saved this this thing that
I'm looking at and I can share it with
you okay so I'm going to share this and
now you can see it right yes yes I can
so this is what we do right mindfulness
community nature and yes and then
there's something really interesting
here so so yeah so we talked about
meditation contemplation then obviously
dialogue we're just in this in this
conversation about dialogue but so what
we've noticed that what people can
comment on about our workshops more than
anything else is the sense of community
yeah yeah you you you asked me this
question last time we talked to like
what is the community practice right but
I hadn't done that explicitly but it is
implicitly or was becoming more
explicitly part of what we were doing so
one of the things is actually a
dialoguing practice and this has been
quite interesting as a development so
traditionally in my workshops I would
tell a lot of sort I would do a lot of
kind of lecture about the theory and
that
in the practice right so people could
put it in in context and gain the
insight out of the physical practice so
now I went to train with Mark Walsh in
June and he had this practice of just
having people after a drill have one
minute to share their insights and then
he'd ask a few leading questions to help
people do that right so we adopted this
when we when we cool when we taught this
summer and it was really interesting how
the Amplatz that I used to feel like I
had to share with people herself but
there was Jerry by the group and I got
everyone talking so we drove a real
interest in dialogue the other aspect of
these community things is we found this
storytelling has this enormous power as
a teacher as I've soared stories in
myself and then once i encountered
jordan Peterson's work actually telling
old mythological stories and can
actually work
and then I've got retreat down here
itself because like I don't know how to
describe the whole container of these
things but when you go away with people
and you make food and you and you do the
dishes together and you go
Sano's whatever it is oh yeah you're
getting sick yeah your synchronized it
up in the powerful waves yeah I get that
that's very good and then the body to
body practices of course fit as a
community development tool as well yeah
and then this one is something that new
and kind of breaking things down but I
wrote down here your four ways of
knowing right propositional Oh
respectable and participatory and I was
just looking through how I've helped
people understand nature in in the
workshops that we did and then also how
my my my colleague Kyle Cox Oh Kyle is
one of our teachers so he's been one of
my students for many years now but he is
also a trained teacher under the will
nurse awareness school method from Enoch
a wilderness awareness school so he
teaches so I noticed that what I do a
lot is what I would call nature
knowledge so it's propositional so
propositional knowledge about here's
what to look for so that a tree branch
doesn't break here's you know what the
local ecology is like here's all this
stuff right and then what Kyle brings is
things like sits
which is awareness training like
meditation ah in orientation toward
nature how do I recognize what is the
like the furthest sound of a bird that I
can hear right what are the birds saying
and you know what is what type of water
sounds are happening all those things
learning to move zoom that awareness
skin and out beside what's it called
again oh if I can't quite read it what's
it called it's it's something it's
spotting sit spotted I'm cool oh and
there's a play on the word spotting I
get that oh that's very good I like that
that's very clever well sorry I mean
that is a complimentary fashion it's not
mine I think it may come from a teacher
named John Junger may proceed yeah I
learned this from my friend Simon tapper
I mentioned before and Kyle and they you
can have a walking meditation practice
where you're where yeah I thought people
walking that hunting-gathering right
wait
I'm also connecting to these problems
these things and and and you need like
fire-making and primitive stuff so
that's where we're we bring the nature
in specifically wow that's very good I
like that that's very interesting
so here's I wanted to tell you this
interesting story about like the power
of the it's called the participatory
perspectival which is also something I'm
just starting to understand but um so I
asked Kyle to teach bird languages and I
expect him to walk through the woods
with the students and describe to them
what type of songs birds sing and help
them recognize this and he sets up this
game where everyone pretends to be a
bird in the forest
oh there's demonic that's very cool
that's very cool
yeah and and I'm very tired because it's
kind of like I teach for three days and
then it's Kyle's day to leave the
wilderness awareness and so I'll just
like go take a nap sometimes so I'm like
not really into running around
pretending to be a bird but there's
birds and there's weasels and there's
hawks and stuff when there's this whole
structure of the game so then I go and I
sleep and I come back and ask people
like okay you know how was it then like
I was one of most amazing things now and
like people are just talking about in
their awareness of the birds and what's
happening is so massively
and oh that's fantastic and it's yeah so
the generate to recognize process which
is really cool you know just become the
thing generated and then you are much
more capable of recognizing that's very
that's very cool this perspectival and
participatory knowing it's so shobana to
write in yes yeah that's really that's
really cool you're doing really
interesting stuff thank you
yeah not just me I mean Kyle that's
Kyle's stuff you all I bet you
collectively you're your group and by
the way I want to acknowledge the way
you share credit I think that's
excellent awesome thank you that's one
thing I really admire about you as well
thank you so yeah so so yeah so then
this is what we do and you know we're
trying to get people these ways of
knowing and then essentially all of this
is oriented towards creating meaning in
people's life and I look at and there's
an interesting thing that I've been
wanting to discuss with you I I just
came across I came across this actually
in a conversation with another of our
friends Erin who's one of my apprentices
with evolved with play but he made the
distinction between being and becoming
and you've talked about the having mode
and the being mode and it feels like
there's some distinction here between
being and becoming as well well I I
actually say that I think the being mode
should be better understood as the
becoming mode it's the mode in which
you're trying new you these are the
needs that are met by developing by
going through a process of self
transformation and it's where aspiration
and appreciation are playing much more
important roles than you know control
and manipulation so yeah III I think why
my from and others wanted to use the
being mode it's because of the way in
which and this overlaps with hided or
who had an influence on from of course
the idea that we recover our sense of
being and if we could bring if we can
bring back the being as you know as the
the gerund the active not being as a
static thing but being all I don't want
to say processes because it's deeper
than a process but you understand what
I'm trying to convey is something much
more dynamic and so when we're in
developmental modes we have to we have
to we have to learn how to disclose
aspects of our being so that the world
can dispose more deeply disclose aspects
of its being so the being in the
becoming are very deeply intertwined in
that way I hope that made some sense
yeah yeah so I wanted to rephrase in
like I think I can use your language and
tell me if this makes sense so it's as
if the way that we think about being
like ontology has become purely a
propositional yes and what you're saying
is that to like truly engage in
philosophy a-- we have young cover the
participatory and perspectival being so
that we are engaged in it not just
observing it exactly i mean that was
that was very well put I completely
agree with what you just said and I
think that I think that's that that's
exactly exactly right yes so this being
and becoming distinction that we make
there's an observation in why there's a
distinction so the first thing is when
you're training there's the there's the
experience of the training and how it is
right so I am in a state right and then
there's how it transforms me over time
yes now if I become hyper focused on
being in the state that I am in now then
I don't for myself transformation
effectively in the future yeah i hyper
focus on the transformation then I never
get to enjoy what I'm trying to become
right and so that's that's that's what I
talk about the symbolic aspect of this
the relationship between your current
self and the divine double to to use
more traditional language yeah you have
to have that you have to have that
symbolic relationship between the two
selves if you'll allow me that language
now I haven't questioned the latest one
I'm like forty minutes into it I think
but you were talking about this you know
about literally like basically being
coming the idea of the divine double
exactly
most recently listening to so it what it
feels like to me is
people I think people need an archetypal
aim right this is sort of what your your
- yeah I think well I think yeah and I
would just hesitated because I think
it's a genus species thing I think the
Union notion of the archetypes is one
species of ways in which people have
crafted symbolism around the divine
double yeah so I mean the thing is your
current self causes the future self but
your future self has normative authority
over your occurrence itself and sort of
getting those getting the sort of the
appropriate respect for each side of
that is it is the virtue that we're
trying to cultivate in people when we're
trying to teach the proper exploration
yeah so I'll share a little story ed
this will be a familiar with a lot of
the viewers but it will help ground the
conversation so I came into parkour and
I
I found something in parkour that was
very meaningful to me and there was this
idea of a philosophy of Concord that I
that that I seized on but I couldn't
quite fully grasp it didn't quite go
here completely and so I think that what
I did was I ended up essentially
reframing parkour in the sport frame
right in this frame that you know we
were talking about maybe descends from
the national Roman ash list and romantic
you know period of of the 19th century
yeah but in that frame you know it's
very you know well perhaps not so
romantic it's very it's very much like
goals right we're going here and and so
it became all about SMART goals specific
measurable actionable realistic time
sensitive right and and so I set up all
these goals and then there was this
conflict because the thing that I want
that was I was truly motivated to be
wasn't the thing that I had set out to
write write write all of my goals were
best served by like training in the gym
so I could go compete in other people
students but when I was deeply motivated
by was going to play in the woods
right and so I followed my motivation
out of the woods I went deep into play
as my kind of primary thing and it was
really transformational I made a massive
progress but at a certain point it
became it became stagnant and and I also
started getting injured and I started
feeling like I needed this sense of
where I was going again that's actually
basically when I encountered Jordan
Peterson's work or whose I actually had
started to articulate very similar ideas
I remember I wrote this essay called the
self-worth of steaming you can check out
the video on my youtube page which was
all about the idea that that that
self-esteem is kind of the wrong thing
to aim at we have to remit creating a
self that we would yeah yeah that's the
aspirational self of Socrates rather
than the true self that you're born with
from in romantist in standard models of
Romanticism exactly very much so so so
we started saying okay we need you we
need to be akin at something and then it
was like well winning at sport or having
a specific skill is actually too narrow
of an 18 it doesn't really doesn't
really encompass what the person it has
to be about how those things transform
you and what are they transforming you
into and well that's that's what this is
this this thing is about so uh so so
yeah so I became very interested in the
idea the hero's journey and that
confrontationally us and how that that
that aim gives us meaning so uh so so I
don't want to them to have to look at
this forever so I need to go through
this a little bit quicker okay sorry no
no no it's great and it's been wonderful
so so okay so we have the being mode
right or what's more being oriented here
ease immediately when you engage in
these practices it affords something
Ford's a deep connection to things that
are meaningful to us ya know play is
intrinsically meaningful and motivating
right movement has a meaning being in
nature is meaningful being with a tribe
of like-minded people engaging something
all of that is powerful in the moment
but then it changes you because it gives
you awareness of self right yes then we
learn our own personality come to
recognize what deeply motivates us we
improve our embodiment right and we
develop a positive relationship with our
body which is something so many people
are missing in our culture right review
our bodies through the lens of something
else right it's excellent
yes I think very deeply can be very
deeply alienated if your body matters
mostly to you because of how other
people see it you're essentially
alienated from the most from you know
the most fundamental aspect of yourself
yes yes so so this is where being is
becoming becoming and then over time we
have this idea that we're transforming
our character right so we consider own
character strands for me you can call it
self transcendence so we can call this
the development of the heroic self right
right these practices we are trying to
afford ourselves these connections and
this transformation that's great I agree
with that
so we talked about something also an
ally gets to that the work I did with
Leo about internalizing the sage and now
there was a lot of these wisdom
traditions like stoicism where you're
trying to internalize Socrates as so the
Socrates serves as a internalized symbol
of the of the future self of the sacred
second self or the divine double but
because Socrates also has a
semi-independent existence
Socrates can challenge you and and and
motivate you
it's not just an egocentric mirror sort
of narcissistically reflecting back to
yourself kind of thing Socrates that is
Damon right so yes yes yes very much so
I'm gonna put this back up then because
that was a perfect segue into what we're
talking about next which is so the
reason that I actually reached out to
you to specifically talk right now was
that I was I was working with folks on
our online course and they were asking
me questions like why can't I do X scale
and I didn't have any video of them
doing the scale so I started saying well
you know it's like a lack of skill so
of physical ability or it's a emotional
psycho-emotional issue right and then I
noticed that that had mapped this idea
of what are the archetypal attributes of
the archetypal representations of the
heroic character that we're trying to
develop so I had you know a switch from
the source the last few years we have
told these heroic narratives right
they've told these stories and we've
mapped the idea of the movement practice
towards like it's like the confrontation
with the dragon in the heroic literature
that was cool but then people were like
what what what is it in more depth what
is it that that gives you that capacity
to confront the hook figure and so we
started looking at what are the
different archetypes of the hero so I
started seeing that there was this
combination here because we talked about
for heroic archetypes at the autumn
retreat now that I am then I had come
study them that gave me an inspiration
for where we were going then I saw that
this was kind of a line and the reason I
I I reached out to you that was because
it didn't align perfectly and I was
trying to figure out how it aligned
right so I but but what we ended up
doing so we started saying if we think
of Horace as an archetype of vision
where does vision sit in our struggle
right it's like well before if we think
of we think of a movement practice as a
as a way of embodying and cultivating
the capacity of the self in general to
address a problem right first the first
problem that you have with a problem is
can you see that it's there yeah I mean
that's that's sort of more like at the
level of like relevance realization and
Horace is often represented as a
capacity for attention of many other
things as well of course and it's out
for assistive course capable of flight
which in the overview but also zooming
in so yeah yeah there's there's many
figures that have that role yeah but
yeah the the the capacity with the the
- - as you said to develop that honing
relevance realization so you have
insight so you see into the situation
well and powerfully yeah I think that's
crucial yeah
so in in the parkour we have this
problem division right and I think it's
the thing that that that is a problem
many people are facing but we've
recognised it right in a certain way
which is when you decide that you want
to practice parkour you start looking
around you and you can't find
necessarily things that look like what
you saw in the video
all right and so so over time you
cultivate this ability to see how the
spaces around you afford you moving
potentials oh I see that's very
interesting so you're doing this sort of
respectable transformation where you're
that's really interesting so you're
trying to train yourself to pick up on
affordances that you originally can't
pick up on that's what you're basically
saying and and what's interesting about
this too is that like I found urban
provision developed very quickly even
though I go into the woods the the
environment is relatively not complex
right you can see it's a highly
predictable highly predictable moving
the nature is actually to this day even
after you know ten years of being
focused on nature eight years whatever
it is it's harder for me to see what is
afforded by a new tree or a new set of
rocks than concrete obstacles I have to
go and physically embed myself in that
environment in order to create the
vision to reimagine the space right
that's really cool and so yeah so we you
know there's this um I'll be familiar
with a new doll loop no no you mentioned
to it yeah it took me to perform yeah
okay so I'll go over that again I think
it's it's interested me because I just
see these these common patterns showing
up and all these to replace them really
interesting and how they all come
together but the loop is the insight of
a military strategist john-boy
we used the Air Force and he basically
recognized like every combative
situation in every come out of situation
you face the problem of incomplete
information this is truth everywhere in
life and he even broke this down to
basically Heisenberg's uncertainty
principle goggles incompleteness theorem
and and what was the other one oh the
thing is the second law of entropy right
basically on these we we you will always
have incomplete information right as
soon as the information gets to you it's
already decrypted its model says it's
already degraded you know and you can't
see everything from within whatever
frame you adopt so so but the big thing
was that in order to continuously solve
problems first you have to be able to
observe accurately what the problem is
vision second you have to be able to
orient effectively to it a problem
formulation then you have to make clear
decisions and act so whether we're going
to side act interestingly within the
parkour community we evolved essentially
a similar sequence which we call feeling
the call of the jump so you observe that
a jump is possible you then assess the
jump and then either before or after
assessment depending on the gentleman
you begin to feel fear mmm and then you
have a process that allows you to
overcome fear which is generally
visualization breathing shaking some
sort of ritualized behavior that allows
you to shift out of that fear state
everybody you act and so if Emily you
could say well the first thing is is
observation right and then essentially
all the rest is like how you overcome
the problem and get to the signal okay
find that really interesting
and then like there's almost a problem
before that which is how to see the per
call of the jumps that could call to you
yeah exactly
it's going to say yeah and so this is
this is where we're the archetype of
vision is right and then yes the next
would be like understanding the problem
right like I can see that this jump
this calls to me but how would it be
done right right
and there's the skillfulness to over to
actually do it and then it's like it
doesn't matter how perfect a jump you
have if the jump is just way too large
either the legs can't make it
you just don't happen but the last thing
is you're you know you can see it you
understand what needs to be done you
have the skill to know how to do it you
have the physical capacity to do it can
you psycho-emotional regulate yourself
to be able right but and so on
interestingly we had talked about for
heroic archetypes at at the retreat as
horace of his vision socrates was logos
and then lou celtic hero celtic god was
the embodiment of skillfulness right but
no in an irish mythology and what's in
the book of the invasions Luke is is
sort of a young hero up-and-coming he
goes to taro which is the capital of
that of the toy and he asked for
entrance and they asked him well in
order to come in here you have to be
really good at something and so he
starts listing off his skills and he
lifts off all of the skills that were
like pertinent in early medieval Ireland
and they keep telling him oh we've got a
we've got a carpenter we've got a Smith
we've got a soldier you got a soothsayer
we've got a poet we've got a harp player
we've got a chess player or whatever and
at the end of it he says do you have
anyone who can do all of these oh no you
can come in and they're like to lead the
battle and then he confronts what turns
out to be his own grandfather and
destroys him and that's new so so Lucas
our idea of skillfulness and then we
talked about Christ as a figure of Agape
and and so initially I was like this
Christ map to this emotional regulation
piece right and it didn't feel quite
right well I have something to say about
that if you want to hear it now can I
finish what I'm saying I really might uh
but what what what occurred to me is
actually if you take this set of heroic
capacities you can have all of them then
you can be evil
mmm-hmm if you're oriented to do the
wrong things than being able to see to
see a problem understand the problem
effectively solve the problem have the
strength to do that and have the
emotional regulation to do it can be
applied to the most horrific horrific
things I mean but then the idea was that
you know essentially what we came up
with was you know Socrates is actually
kind of a combination figure for us he's
the emotional regulation and the
understanding Horace's vision Luke is
coordination skill you could use
Hercules or Thor as representations of
strength and obviously you know heroes
contain different elements but it's just
that's the story that we can tell to
contain this insight for people and then
at the highest end it's like if this
isn't in service of Agape then then it's
not ultimately leading us towards heroic
character good night you know for the
audience this isn't me telling them that
they need to go join the church and
become you know about Christians I'm not
I'm non-theist as you are but I think
this is true and I also think that like
Metta meditation which we learned
earlier which we talked about earlier
it's actually one of the powerful
pathways to to cultivating this specific
so that's that's this map that I created
this is what I wanted to share with you
and get you thought that money oh I like
that I like that I like that you
basically anticipated what I was going
to say so that's good I was going to say
that you know agape sort of bleeds
between you know it's it's a kind of
soft force and first of all what you
want with sever your self-regulation you
don't want it to be in cranek you want
it to be soft force on it right you you
and and the way I describe that if you
want to come to a place where you're
tempted by the good right that your
salience landscape is constantly
tempting you to work is the good and
then and then Paul presents agape as
exactly the transform st. Paul is the
best form of software so because we're
constantly being tempted towards the
good of trying to create as much meaning
and as many meaning makers as we
possibly can and so that's how exactly
yeah I think you you articulated what I
was gonna say quite well actually
beautiful yeah I love that idea of
softer sin there you have been tempted
to the good and I was thinking about him
we actually thought it was interestingly
in line with like flow
the idea yes it is I mean you're talking
a lot about this Sensibility
transcendent and sensibility
transformation and but you're right you
have to have something that organizes it
all together in that aspiration yeah but
what are we aspiring to well we're
altima aspiring to meaning making and
the cultivation of meaning makers that's
what we're altima this is how this whole
thing right right
grounds itself because there's nothing
else beyond that that's grounding it
yeah so that's like--that's logos the
thing that yeah way that we can
articulate and give rise to order and
agape which guides us towards order that
is actually to the good against you have
that faith that everyone we interact
with has the capacity to come into an
order that is better yes I think that's
well said and and and if we didn't have
if if if if we were not already grounded
in logos and agape we couldn't do any of
this in any ways part of you know part
of the ancient notion of pride or hubris
as a sin is a refusal to acknowledge
that we are already beholding to logos
and agaves and we should acknowledge
that and then put ourselves right
into a participatory relationship with
it rather than pretending that we don't
need logo Sena got that yeah I think
that's fundamentally important so one
one thing that occurs to me I have but
he talks about the aspect of the heroic
the heroic person and he talked about
the logos right and that's represented
by the mouth and the tongue right vision
is represented by the eyes and he talks
about those as you know if you look at a
homunculus of the body this is what's
most represented the other thing is the
hand understanding the hand grasping
yeah but for me that's the body too
right yes very much very much yes and
that's what I see is missing so often
these conversations about meaning is how
it gets grounded in the body oh you see
that's right that's why
emphasize the contact epistemology so
much because the contact epistemology
reminds us about the embodied embedded
map as well as opposed to the sort of
sort of spectating yak toriel
epistemology I'm not sure how to talk to
you about this we were talking about
nature like how does natural movement
Natural Park or Chi create connection
with nature and and Peterson has this
analogy of of resolution right imagine
that you have high pixels or low pixels
right like the morphix elated your thing
is and since some the more meaning you
have extracted from I'm singing like
imagine the experience of a tree right
you have me showing you the picture of
the tree and you can say oh that's a
beautiful tree right I I would love to
see that truth walking through the park
and see that tree and that would be more
meaningful it would be more real having
had that experience participated in
being near the tree doing more real but
when you move in the tree when you map
it with your body when you map how it
affords your body moving from space to
space this creates a layer of meaning
that has greater depth and you can go in
another even more but it's like if you
know what animals live that what yep
that proposed you know how it's used you
know what kind of timber it makes but
all of these things are are built up
into meaning and it's like it feels like
we we have become divorced from this
incredible world of meaning that exists
all around us that were simply blind to
yes I agree that's why I've been trying
to articulate this notion of sacredness
as a deep kind of connectedness to the
inexhaustible as opposed to older models
of completion and perfection which
tended to be very static and tended to
give us the idea that there was sort of
a a final state that we were trying to
get to an achieved but if we can I think
what you're doing if you'll allow me is
I think you're trying to re articulate
this notion of sacredness as this
right there's this fount of just more
and more intelligibility more and more
meaning more and more connectedness what
you're saying is of course not just
intellectual connectiveness it's the
embodied in embedded connectedness and
that's exactly it they're like can we
get back to right
that sense of that are our ongoing
capacity to evolve our connection to the
world
can be coupled to the fact that the
world can continually generate new
connections for us it's inexhaustible in
that way and to understand sacredness in
that fashion that's that's precisely
what I'm trying to articulate that idea
I see what you're doing is you're using
nature and I don't mean in some sort of
you know you know pantheistic paganism
or something like that we're trying to
reintroduce nature as something that can
be experienced as sacred as a sacred
experience for people and I think that's
very important and and the fact that we
see it it doesn't involve people having
to sort of commit to a Creed it has to
involves them committing to a code of
conduct well because if they don't
commit to a code of conduct they're
gonna hurt themselves right but but but
but it involves it involves a different
way it involves a different way of
getting people to we inhabit sacredness
as opposed to just argue about the
propositions that have been referring to
sacredness does that make any sense what
I'm trying
when I'm trying to articulate yeah
absolutely it's it's it's very
interesting I mean so my old business
partner Tyson when we started our
parkour gym together
he um he always joked that we should
just turn parkour into a church right
[Laughter]
but now like people will be like well
what are you creating you're creating a
religion um
and I was like well no not a credo but I
to help people connection religio well
that's that's exactly right and that's
why making that distinction I think is
really important
and and you know and you you're creating
a very complex myth thought mythos right
we're even talking about using
mythological figures in order to afford
people coming into a more to
participatory awareness of eligio and
how if they enhance that connectedness
they get this experience of it being
intrinsically meaningful but again in
put it in this in this sense in which
it's III become sort of as you know I've
become hesitant with the word meaning
because it sounds so subjective and I
really want to that's why I like what
you've been saying this sense of
increasing connectedness and that's what
I'm trying to get it it's the kid and
even though we're connectedness sound
static and fixed and but I'm trying to
it's more this ongoing mutually
accelerating disclosure that's why it's
more much more like love than it is by
making a statement yeah you help me
you're helping people you have that
right and I don't mean this romantically
man we've trivialize the word with
remittances but you're helping people to
fall in love with sort of the depths of
connect through the depths of
connectedness that they can find in the
natural world they're they're falling
back in love with being and I think
that's the ultimate way in which we have
to respond to nihilism we can argue and
we can make philosophical propositions
but people have to learn how to deeply
fall back in love with reality that's
what they need and again and you know I
don't mean this romantically I I mean in
this in in the sense of a sacred kind of
love it ironically ya know that really
that like you know that struck home for
me right like especially because going
back to the idea that agape is the
principle that yes highest access to the
good right yes it's it's it's kind of
like the idea that that the proper
practice is a practice that bring that
that continually helps you fall in love
with all of the most important things in
life yes yes yes that that seems
extraordinarily powerful it's
interesting one of the you know let me
just I want to let that one sink in
because so after one of my seminars one
of the students said to me that it was
it was like having gone for a walk on
the beach for years and years and years
and I'm getting to go surfing
first time mmm and how the the beach now
suddenly became so much more me like
yeah you form a literal way like yeah I
know these things about the waves
that's propositional but not only do I
know these things about the waves I have
felt what it is to be in those waves I
know this millions landscape of what
those both waves mean right like I know
when when a wave behaves this way yes
yes afforded me this thing yes and I
know then also what that experience is
mmm-hmm right I really I really have
struggled with distinction between
participatory and perspectival and one
of your recent lectures you were talking
about your old model of wisdom which
didn't include participatory right that
the procedural sorry um propositional
gives you rules procedural gives you
roles
Matthew teens routines routines right
men men and then perspectival gives you
roles and I wasn't wait what's what's
after that but and then it finally came
together it for me it was like mothers
should feed their children when they cry
is is a proposition right knowing how to
warm up the milk and put it in the in
the in the model that's a procedure
right right you could understand the
proposition not on how to actually feed
the baby that's right that's right
and then a baby crying is a salience
landscape that becomes especially
meaningful to anyone who has had a baby
or they had a baby right and that that
is it that is an experience that is
shared right that perspective is true of
all the all the class of mothers but
what that meant to that individual woman
at that time is the participatory right
I actually identify the way she
changes our identity so she's
identifying with the child that's that's
the participant every right yep well she
her her process of being and the child's
process of being become deeply coupled
and interpenetrating so her knowing of
herself and her knowing of her child are
not distinguishable from each other they
mutually interpenetrate and afford each
other yeah so then to look at the
practice the movement practice right to
do a jumper revolt or something I can
tell you in this situation this is the
appropriate jump revolt or swing or
whatever to do that would be
propositional right knowing in your body
having the skill to do it is procedure
procedure right being able to recognize
it within a given base is perspective
situational awareness that's respect
idle yeah but then the way that it
transforms you is the participatory and
let's we seem afraid and that goes back
to that underneath and grounding this is
your aspiration to your hill role acute
yourself and you knowing and becoming
because it's a Socratic self-knowledge
that that future self is bound up with
you knowing and getting access to the
depths of the world that's what I mean
about the depths of you and the depths
of the world your knowing of your depths
and your knowing of the depths of the
world are like the mother and the child
being identified with each other they
are mutually inter penetrating and
mutually affording yeah that's that's
beautiful so another thing that's
occurred to me with the symmetries
interesting is a while ago I read this
essay on Jitsu versus Dao we talked
about this not to me I don't think so
the idea was simply that traditionally a
many martial arts started as essentially
like trade skills right and you know I I
you know IQ jutsu was was a trade skill
for someone who had to use a sword in
battle that's what it meant it meant
when procedurally when my life is on the
line I can use this thing to try and
save myself however
there was a point at which and this
happened in different ways people
recognized that the process of of going
through the procedure that Jitsu
afforded a dough and the dough is a way
I know
dough in Japanese is Dow in Chinese see
right there
and so I catch it soon becomes Aikido
right and you see the same thing in the
internal martial arts you know you're a
Tai Chi Chuan practitioner right mm-hmm
you practice things because you know
their martial skills
that's only one layer of the practice
and if raid1 and ba gua ing are armed
Taoist arts right they're deeply
connected with this whole ecology of
practices of specific meditations and
body and parent practices all the Chi
kung young you know traditional
medicines yeah all of that was was sort
of part of this this this world and and
what I recognized when I read that was
that parkour in its its initial
development was actually dough oriented
and that the dough was not sufficiently
articulated well oh I say world so all
we saw was the Jitsu so there's
something in vaulting and doing these
things but we didn't see was that the
young men who started this they were
immigrant you know mixed-race kids
visible minorities traumatic backgrounds
you know they're having tried many of
them having trouble in school they were
you know they would do that they could
have gotten involved in gangs and lots
of gangs in their neighborhoods and the
bad news of Paris and they they needed
someplace to go it was away it was an
aspirational way strong men and that was
the purpose of purpose yeah yeah how do
I test myself and become this thing that
I'm that I want to be the there was you
know 912 founders of parkour and at a
certain point David Bell who's the most
famous split with the rest over a circus
performance but the rest of them then
adopted a name for themselves comb which
is Yama Kazi which is a long haul
which is West African language which
means strong man strong mind strong
spirit strong spiritual body strong we
had something like that an idea you can
see the aspiration the first I let this
is the transformation of the self right
very much and so it feels like in many
ways what I have been creating with the
vault is play it is a return to the DAO
right yes I agree with that and and this
came up for me because I was thinking
about that idea you had of the the
sacredness as the inexhaustible mm-hmm
and like even when I hate fishing when I
started telling people the Dragons story
and connecting it to the idea of the the
pursuit of the heroic self I always like
to caveat it by saying but always
remember the DAO that can be spoken is
not the internal demo okay right what I
can reveal to you about the orientation
of your practice never will will be
sufficient to contain all of what the
practices or can mean to you so don't
get too attached to it and now I feel
like I'm kind of tangentially running in
many different directions because you
you see the squad around and the way
that you were describing that that that
um the way in which being is sort of is
both an exhaustible and and withdrawing
from you and also get or signing in yeah
yeah at the same time that that
relationship with being and being able
to to come more and more into that
relationship with being is maybe the
orientation of the practice and that's
why the idea of movement practice as Dao
came through for me as something that I
needed to share with you I think it's
excellent I mean it might be then that
that there's a higher-order connection
going on here because I think what you
just articulated was excellent but it's
as you know I brought that language up
to trying to talk a bit about Heidegger
and also the kind of stuff that's
happening in the circling practice which
is this
your personal dialogue dialogical
practice and yet there seems to be this
higher-order point of convergence I'm
not trying to do I'm not trying to
collapse everything I'm trying to do
like a small world network there's this
high reporting convergence that they can
all talk to each other out and then they
write I'm get the compression you get
the compression to what a share and then
you get the variation out into the
specific practices yeah I'm gonna have
to take a quick break my daughter's okay
I'll be rolled okay so we'll pause this
for a second okay thank you very much
okay well guys we have an extra guest
today special guest this is Katie so
hopefully she will let us have a little
chat Katie okay my other daughter okay
thank you for for your patience it's
live kids I mean I've had I've had young
kids so I know it I know it but really
enjoy it anyway and I mean this is a
couple it's like living with elves I
mean it's just an amazing amazing um
look great before we're running out of
time and so when my trying to shed
things I I just need to say something
about this like and and this is really
I'm just being bitter since fear I'm
rarely impressed by the work you've done
and I'm not trying to in any way take
credit for your ideas or your insight
but I see also in a lot of ways if this
just feels fair to you in which you're
making use of a lot of my ideas and what
you're doing what you're doing with it
it is it's just impressive it's really
impressive it's it's like if if you
allow me an analogy I might be doing
this science when you're doing this
amazing engineering that is just like
like it's exemplary it's exemplary I
want people to see what you're doing and
understand what you're doing as a clear
example of the kind of stuff I'm talking
about how it's been concretize dand
developed but and how its evolving I
just wanted to say that because it's
very very very impressive work well
thank you I know means a lot to hear
that your work has been really deeply
influential it's been you know
during Peterson gave me a window into
the meaning thing in a way that you know
still had a huge influence in grammar
running into your work has given this
wonderful set of tools I was telling you
before but I i sat down and started like
writing absolutely your keys I could
make you organize where I'm using them
and how that's how those those those
threads and my experience with parkour
absolutely a research you know you know
flow there's some others so many in
there but like you know you hold a very
high place in in in the set of
influences that are giving me the
insights to create what we're creating
and and also that the example that
you've given and your friendship has
been extraordinary
Doug thank you thank you well if that's
was ex deeply reciprocated for not I was
I just wanted I just want to say that
because like I say one of the one of the
legitimate criticisms I'm not trying to
dodge it that people maybe hit my work
is and it's often very abstract right
and it's a gift but what do I do
and you know I try to address that as
best I can but if you're doing a much
better job at addressing that then I
have done a potentially ever could do so
I wanted to thank you for that as well
well that is quite the high praise I'm
gonna put that on my website oh well
that's fine you plea please do lose dude
I am I wanted to I mean it may be time
to close a conversation here but I
wanted to address like the last time we
spoke you or you're asking me to to pay
attention to your dialogues with with
with guys thanks doc yes very much
I thought this was interesting and I
wanted to share my experience with you
and hopefully this will be interesting
items as well um it was initially hard
for me to listen to a guy because I find
that what is it tractive to me a lot of
the times is that facility with juggling
propositions or having a clear set of
propositions that you're offering and
when I was listening to talk to you he's
not offering so much of his
so much of his propositions that's right
that's for what what what comes through
is actually the example of participating
in what he's trying to create yes very
much
this is another thing and I actually
listen to my you know it was nice to
listen to my friend Mark Walsh's
interview with God because then you got
a little bit more of an idea behind
that's right that's right I also just
happened to have another few friends
you've also gotten to circling and so
it's it's been very interesting to take
on some of the ideas and bring that into
to my relationship with my wife but also
thinking about how we use dialoguing has
an immigration enactus because I think
it's it's incredibly valuable and I
think if we are if we're if we're
letting you know we had this
conversation before we started to call
about kind of the grammar of sport and
physical culture and why it might have
been like I've lost the meaning that
should or how it might have added
meanings embedded in it that we don't
really want to keep embedding it that's
right and we can get into that in a
future when I show you some more
research let'em but if we're if we're
choosing a new orientation towards
meaning and it is towards this idea of
the cultivation of the self you
connecting it to the practice of
mindfulness connecting to the practice
of dialogue becomes incredibly powerful
so I'm very interested in what you're
doing with guide and with Jordan Paul
and you recommend all the the listeners
look into that and it's something that
you know I want to know more about and
how we can yeah
facilitating this growth of the dial
logos in relation you know like and this
is this is kind of what I want to offer
that conversation to it's like I think
that if we can get them the embodiments
and we can get me embedding into the
environment and we can connect that to
the dialoguing process so we're getting
that zooming in getting this broader
perspective we're having the evolving
sense like you know I was really good at
that you didn't make it to to the
Ottoman tree because I want I want
yeah yeah no idea and I well you know
I'm showing that I'm deeply committed to
participant observation so I very much
want to do that yeah I thank you for
saying that I recommend especially the
two videos with the four of us with guy
said stock Jordan all myself and
Christopher monster Pietro I think those
two videos especially with with the four
of us because we all we it's much more
like what we're talking about the day
you get Minnie you get the four kinds of
no and I'm not saying each one of us
represents one of the kinds of knowing
or anything ridiculous but all the kinds
of knowing are put into much more
dynamic interaction in a powerful way
which I really I like I said if there's
a there's a thing there the logos comes
and it takes everybody you know into a
place where they can't get to on its own
and and and knowing how to translate
maybe that's the right verb between that
interpersonal and then the way we talked
about how you how you get people into
that kind of dialogic emergence of the
logos with respect to nature in the
environment and getting those two
dialogues to dialogue together I think
is something that I'm deeply interested
in understanding more deeply and the
communication that comes through the
body right yes you know where variation
is how like we've become divorced from
meaning again like if you if I say
something to you here and you can see
and you can hear my tone of voice
there's layers of meanings that are
Deloris that if i said the same thing to
you in text message oh of course
and so one of the things you're picking
up on the circling practices because you
always have in the stereoscopic vision
if you're doing this deep mindful
awareness inward and then you're doing a
deep mindful awareness outward but one
of the things you'll often pick up on is
you'll pick up on the mediating role of
gesture between the propositional and
the perspectival and the way and so very
often people will you'll even see it in
some of the times when I'm talking with
guy and I'll say well you just sort of
you stood back you sort of moved back
and you sort of tilted your head like
he'll call out gesture and you know and
that's that for me is something I want
to
and to that though the the that
reappropriation a react septation of
gesture as a way of bridging between the
propositional aspects of dialogue and
more procedural and the more embodied
aspects of the dialogue and and so
within what we call roughhousing right
we have the layer of communication that
comes where we actually are touching
each other and we learn to a sensitivity
in contact there and and this I think
gives a sensitivity and an awareness you
know the research like as I'm just
writing about this right now
but um you know research shows that
rough-and-tumble play increases capacity
for empathy essentially scores your
ability for theory of mind well yeah
because in training the insula to pick
up on your own interceptive stuff it
coupled to you're trying to get a sense
of where the other person is expressing
their intentionality through how they're
moving yeah that but that makes that
makes very good sense to me
and so it'll be very interesting to
think about how can we get that
connection from the from let's embed
ourselves in the environment let's
create our container let's move with
each other let's move and then let's
create dialogue right and how does that
that generate the meaning yeah I'm aware
that were just about out of time here
but I deeply appreciate the conversation
well I I really really enjoyed it right
I mean it was good for me I got to spend
a lot of time and I I mean this is a
good sense I guess it's not a lot of
time listening cuz I got really deeply
interested and I said what you're doing
and that's why I provoked that reaction
and you know that response in me to what
you're doing
so why I'm thank you but I just wanna I
don't know it seems so trite but I just
want to keep encouraging you to do what
you're doing it's really fun it really
helps to have people who sing so I think
my children are are are going to call it
I call an end of this call yeah you need
to move on with your day but we'll chat
again soon no of course my friend we'll
talk it again for sure you can count on
it okay thanks care of my friend
[Music]